(BIRDS CALLING)
(BIRDS CALLING RHYTHMICALLY)
Hey!
# 所有鸟类 披着羽毛 #
All the birds of a feather
# 各有所需 取其所好 #
Do what we love most of all
# 谈及擅长 节奏欢笑 #
We are the best at
rhythm and laughter
# 大爱狂欢 原因自了 #
That's why we love Carnaval!
(CHEEPING)
# 万物皆明 轻声和唱 #
Call so clear we can sing to
# 他们口中 沙滩阳光 #
Sun and nature's big moon
# 伴随音乐 爱意倔强 #
Dance to the music, Passion and love
# 于众展示 自己强项 #
Show us the best you can do!
# 众人在此 激情点亮 #
Everyone here is on fire
# 起身参与 欢度时光 #
Get up and join in the fun
# 素昧平生 共舞欢畅 #
Dance with a stranger,Romance and danger
# 仿佛有人 挥动法杖 #
Magic can happen For real
# 就在里约 实现梦想 #
In Rio, All by itself!
# 你能看到
You can't see
它的美妙 #
it coming
# 别的地方 发现不了 #
You can't find it anywhere else!
# 就在里约 全部看到 #
lt's real in Rio
# 其余事情 你也知晓 #
And know something else
# 事到临头
You can't feel
你都料到 #
it happening
# 感同身受 你全明了 #
You can't feel it all by yourself!
(BIRDS SQUAWKING)
(EXCLAIMING)
(SQUAWKING SOFTLY)
(CHIRPS)
(HIP HOP MUSIC
PLAYING ON STEREO)
(RATTLING)
(SIGHING)
(CLICKING)
(CHEEPS)
(HIP HOP MUSIC CONTINUES)
(EXCLAIMING)
(CHIRPS SADLY)
(GASPS)
没事的 没事的
lt's okay. lt's okay.
(SHUSHING)
我会照顾你的
l'll take care of you.
拼写大赛冠军!
(BUZZING)
(MOANING)
破闹钟!
Stupid clock.
(GRUNTING)
(ALARM CONTINUES)
(HIGH-PITCHED BEEPING)
Huh?
(CAR ALARM SOUNDING)
(CAR ALARM STOPS)
早上好 布鲁
Good morning, Blu.
(BURPS)
Eww.
来
Come here!
泰勒·布鲁·甘德森
Tyler Blu Gunderson!
你知道这些维他命对你有好处
You know these vitamins are good for you.
喔
Ooh!
这是什么?
What's this?
(SQUAWKS)
Gotcha!
(MIMICKING POLICE SIREN)
(WHOOPING)
(MIMICS PIRATE)
(BOTH lMITATING EXPLOSION)
享用新书吧
LINDA: Enjoy the new book!
谢谢招待 琳达
Thanks, Linda!
再见了
Bye, now.
是的 妈妈 我会去的
Yes, Mom,
l'd love to visit,
但是谁来照顾布鲁呢?
but who would
take care of Blu?
妈妈 他们没有鹦鹉呆的地方
Mom! They don't have kennels for parrots.
这是你的热巧克力 布鲁
Here's your hot chocolate, Blu!
告诉我你喜欢就行
Just how you like it.
因为把布鲁丢给别人我不放心
Plus, l don't trust leaving Blu with just anyone.
没 我没给它请保姆
No, l don't have a bird-sitter.
啊 这就是生活
(SIGHING)This is the life.
(SNIFFS)
棉花糖和可可的比例恰如其分
The perfect marshmallow-to-cocoa ratio.
一 二 三 四 五... 六块!
One, two, three,four, five, six.
Mmm.
(CACKLING)
好吧 这不是我最喜欢的呆鸟嘛
Well, well, if it isn't my favorite nerd bird.
很... 很好笑 真是成熟的表现
Very funny.Real mature.
嗨 宠物鸟 今年你要往哪儿迁徙?
Hey, pet!Where you migrating to this year?
The "Broad-First" nook?
你那个"最宽阔"的角落?
想扔雪球的话请便
Throw all the snowballs you want.
反正我有神奇的保护盾 叫做"玻璃"
l'm protected by this magical force-field called glass.
能让我在这里暖呼呼的
lt's what keeps us so toasty and warm in here
你们就在外面冻着吧...
while you guys are out there freezing your...
(SCATTING MOCKINGLY)
干得漂亮
Classy.
(TULIO EXCLAIMING)
(SPEAKING PORTUGUESE)
(EXCLAIMING)
(MOANING)
你没事吧?
Are you all right?
我还不怎么适应这儿的天气
l'm not really built for this weather.
哦 你要什么书吗?
Oh. Are you looking for some books?
什么书? 不 不是的
Books? No. No.
我长途跋涉六千英里就是为了找他
l have come 6,000 miles looking for him.
(SQUAWKS)
鸟类学博士?
LINDA: Doctor of Ornithology?
哦！
Ooh!
他真漂亮
He's magnificent.
(CHIRPING)
琳达 快救救我 琳达!
Linda? Little help here. Linda!
(SQUAWKING)
哇噢！
Wow!
你竟然可以跟他沟通
You're actually communicating.
没错 我在用
Yes! l introduced myself
他们的方式打招呼呢 逆时针摇摇尾巴羽毛
and shook my tail feathers counter-clockwise
做个自我介绍
thus deferring to his dominance.
我完全没明白
l did not get that at all.
蒙特罗博士...
So, Dr. Monteiro...
别叫我博士 叫我图里奥就行
No "Doctor," please, just call me Tulio.
你知道吗 你的金刚鹦鹉可是稀有品种哦
You know, your macaw is a very special bird.
事实上 据我所知
ln fact, as far as we know,
布鲁是同类中最后一只雄鸟了
Blu is the last male of his kind!
真的吗?
Really?
是的
Yes,
不过最近我们发现了一只雌鸟
and recently, we found a female
我们希望让他们配对
and our hope is to bring the two of them together
来拯救这个物种
to save their species.
哦
(GULPS)Oh.
当然可以 那她什么时候来呢?
Well, yeah, sure, when can she come over?
哦 不不不 她在巴西呢
No, no. She is in Brazil.
布鲁得到里约热内卢来
Blu must come to Rio de Janeiro.
(LAUGHS)
巴西 里约?
Rio? Brazil?
哦 不不不不不不不
No. No, no, no.
我从未让布鲁离开过我的视线 他需要我
l never let Blu out of my sight. He needs me.
不是的 你... 你误会了
No. You misunderstand.
都安排好了
lt's all arranged.
路上你会一步不离地跟着他
You will be with him every step of the way.
当然我也会一直陪着你
And l will be with you.
听着 我知道这是你的工作 但是... 我不能...
Look, l know you're doing your job, but l can't...
呃 布鲁他很特别...
Well, Blu is very particular.
而且我们这有自己的生活
And we have our little routine here
再者 我们并不喜欢旅行
and we're not big on travel.
更何况 他甚至不会飞
Heck, he doesn't even fly!
他必然会飞啊！
But of course he can fly!
他是个完美的雄鸟
He's a perfect specimen.
你要做什么?
What are you doing?
别担心 通常来说 飞行是他们的天性
Don't worry, their natural instincts always take over.
等等 等等 不要!
Wait, wait, wait! No, no!
(SQUAWKING)
呃 总有特例
Well, almost always.
布鲁!
Blu!
你是哪门子的博士啊?
What kind of doctor are you?
你还好吗?
Are you okay?
或许他是被过分驯化了
Perhaps, he's too domesticated.
感谢你移步到我们店里 四处发牢骚
lt was very nice of you to stop in and squawk around
还把我的鸟丢了出去
and throw my bird.
不过现在你该走了
But now it's time for you to go.
我很抱歉 真的很常抱歉 但...
l'm very sorry. l'm very sorry, but...
等一下 等等 琳达 琳达
Wait, wait, Linda. Linda!
这可能是我们最后的机会了
This could be our last chance.
一路顺风
Have a safe flight.
(SIGHING)
琳达 请听我解释啊!
Linda, please, listen to me.
如果我们不这么做
lf we don't do this,
他的种族就会灭亡
his whole species will be gone!
考虑一下吧
Just think about it.
天性
BLU: Natural instincts!
被扔过半个屋子跟天性没有半毛钱的关系
There is nothing natural about being thrown halfway across the room.
哈 我要让他瞧瞧
Well, l'll show him.
我做得到
l can do this.
我只需要计算出一些数据
l just have to work out the physics.
我已经调整了我的角度
l have quadrated my vector angles.
适应了风力
l've adjusted for wind shear.
加强了全部措施
Positive reinforcement.
不错
Good.
好了 检查一下
Okay, let's see.
机翼张开 完美
Flaps open. Perfect.
着陆装置 很好
Landing gear. Check.
尾羽 没问题
Tail flaps. Operational.
实际上 很不错
And, actually, not bad.
准备好了
This is it.
起飞吧
Let's fly.
非常简单
Just keep it simple.
推力 升力 阻力 和耐力
Thrust, lift, drag and weight.
推力 升力 阻力 耐力
Thrust, lift, drag, weight.
推力 升力 阻力...等等
Thrust, lift, drag... Wait!
(EXCLAIMING)
啊！
Ow!
布鲁?
Blu?
(SQUAWKING)
我答应过会一直照顾你 对不对?
l promised l would always look out for you, didn't l?
我有食言过吗?
And have l ever broken a promise?
我也很害怕
l'm scared, too
但若这不是正确的抉择
but l wouldn't make you do this
我也不会强迫你这么做
if it wasn't the right thing to do.
布鲁 你说呢?
What do you say, Blu?
(BOTH lMITATING EXPLOSION)
这才是我勇敢的布鲁
That's my big, brave boy.
我们很快就会回来的
And we'll be back home before we even know it.
“我们这就去里约吧”
(LET ME TAKE YOU TO RIO PLAYING)
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
“如雄鹰般穿越海洋”
Fly over the ocean like an eagle, eagle
“当我们如猎狗般欢乐撒泼”
Then we can chill in my gazebo, gazebo
“我们这就去里约吧”
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
“如雄鹰般穿越海洋”
Fly over the ocean like an eagle, eagle
“当我们如猎狗般欢乐撒泼”
Then we can chill in my gazebo, gazebo
(SONG CONTINUES
lN PORTUGUESE)
你也擦点 布鲁
Your turn, Blu!
你不想晒伤你的"鸟嘴巴"吧
You don't want
to get beak-burn.
哇！
Whoa!
哇！这是要做什么?
Whoa! What is going on here?
你刚好赶上狂欢节
You arrived in time for Carnaval!
狂欢节?
Carnaval?
是的 这是世界上最盛大节日
Yes, it's the biggest party in the world.
你知道的 一个大家跳舞欢乐的日子
You know, a time to have fun and dance!
(BEAT-BOXING)
哦 天啊!
Oh, my!
她是演员吗?
ls she a performer?
不 事实上她是我的牙医
No, in fact, she's my dentist.
巴博萨医生!
Dr. Barbosa!
别忘记用牙线 图里奥
Don't forget to floss, Tulio!
没问题！
You got it!
明天晚上你也来吧 所有人都会打扮成这样
Come tomorrow night,everyone will be dressed like that.
(LAUGHS)
我可不会
Not me.
(BIRDS SINGING)
哦 好吧
Oh, right yeah.
(EXCLAIMS)
我不是当地人
l am not from here.
嘿 尼科 他是个游客
Hey, Nico, he's a tourist!
有意思 你长得一点都不像游客
Funny, you don't look like one.
是吗? 我不像吗?
Really? l don't?
除了你的鼻子上好像有鸽子便便
Except you got pigeon doo-doo on your nose.
哦 不 这是系数为3000的防晒霜
Oh, no, this is just SPF 3000.
那么你是来参加狂欢节的吗?
So, are you here for Carnaval?
事实上我是来这儿相亲的
Actually, l'm just here to meet a girl.
哦...
Oh...
- 哈 泡妞啊?  - 是哦
- A girl! - Yes!
给你点忠告 你一定要主动出击
Little word of advice, you make the first move.
巴西女孩喜欢自信的男人
Brazilian ladies respond to confidence.
哦 没错
Oh, right.
是啊 其实就是吹嘘
Yeah, it's all about swagger.
你一定要挺胸抬头
You got to puff out that chest!
摇着尾巴
Swing that tail!
眯眼凝视 就像一只发情的雄鹰
Eyes narrow, like some kind of crazy love-hawk!
- 但是首先 我们要把你弄出这个笼子  - 为啥?
- But first we got to bust you out. - What?
我开这笼子就像拔汽水罐一样易如反掌
Yeah! l'm gonna pop that cage open like a soda can!
不 不要 等等！
No, no. Wait!
不 不 真的不用
No, no, no, that's okay.
你管这叫拔?
You call that popping?
这玩意儿怪结实的
This thing is robust.
不 不 伙计们 真的 我很好 这个笼子挺棒的
No, no, guys, really, l'm fine. The cage is great.
我很爱它
Love the cage!
好吧 随便你吧
Suit yourself!
别忘了 像个情圣
Don't forget, love-hawk!
(SQUAWKING)
好好 嗯...
Yes, yes, Bem...
你们也是啊
And to you, as well.
“我们这就去里约吧”
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
“如雄鹰般穿越海洋”
Fly over the ocean like an eagle, eagle
“当我们如猎狗般欢乐撒泼”
So we can chill in my gazebo, gazebo
这是我们鸟舍的要地
This is the heart and soul of our aviary.
治疗室
Our treatment room.
(MIMICKING BIRDS)
它们真的很喜欢你哦
They really like you.
(EXCLAIMS)
很喜欢
A lot.
是啊 我就是他们伟大的鸟妈妈
Yes. l'm their great, big mama bird.
Eww.
哇噢！
Wow!
来点吗?
Want some?
哦 不用了
Oh, l'm good.
(SQUAWKING)
这里大多数鸟都是从走私犯的手里救出来的
Many of the birds here were rescued from smugglers.
走私贩?
Smugglers?
是啊 不幸的是
Yes! And unfortunately,
这些可怜的鸟通常都受了伤
the poor birds are often hurt
有些甚至会在走私的途中死掉
or even killed in the process.
但是在精心照料下 它们很快就能好起来
But with proper care, they can be saved.
看这儿 这只可怜的鸟是昨晚救回来的
Look here. This poor guy was found last night.
(SQUAWKING WEAKLY)
嘿 小家伙 你今天看起来不错
Hey, buddy! You're looking great today.
好多了 好多了
Much better, much better!
祝你早日康复
Get well soon!
哦！
Oh!
那么 珠儿在哪?
So, where is Jewel?
我们给她安排了一个特别的房间
We have a special place for Jewel.
她是只非常活泼的鸟
She's a very spirited bird.
没错
l'll say.
这是她干的?
She did that?
真迷人啊 好了 我现在想回家了
Charming. Okay, I want to go home now.
不 别担心
No, no. Don't worry.
我会把你打扮得帅到无可抗拒
l'm going to make you look irresistible.
救命! 救命! 放我出去!
Help! Help! Let me out of here!
(EXCLAIMS)
琳达!
Linda!
或许我应该...
Maybe l should...
不 给他们个机会
No, no. Give it a chance.
(GULPS)
有人吗?
Hello?
我崇尚和平
I come in peace.
哇 她真漂亮
BLU: Whoa. She's beautiful.
他们之前干嘛那么说啊? 她... 好像个天使
What were they talking about? She's like an angel.
这天使离我越来越近了!
An angel who's getting really close...
(SPEAKING PORTUGUESE)
(MUFFLED)
你踩到我喉咙了
You're standing on my throat.
你是美国来的啊
Oh, you're an American.
谢谢
Thanks.
我需要喉咙来说话 所以 多谢了
I need my throat for talking. So, thank you.
你长得很像我
You look like me.
嗨
(HIGH-PITCHED) Hi.
嗨 我叫布鲁
(CLEARING THROAT)
Hi, my name is Blu.
咱俩就像同一个印奶酪的模子刻出来的
Like the cheese with the mold on it.
你知道 奶酪闻起来很臭
You know, that smells really bad.
真是笨呐 笨呐 笨呐
That's stupid. Stupid, stupid, stupid.
快点 我们没多少时间
Come on. We don't have much time.
(EXCLAIMING)
等等 等等 等等!
Wait, wait, wait.
- 准备好了吗?  - 准备好什么? 哦！
- Are you ready? - For what? Oh! Oh.
哦 好啊
Wow. Okay.
自信!大情圣
Confidence. Crazy love-hawk.
好吧
All right.
哇哦 嘿! 你在做什么?
Whoa, what are you doing?
啊? 不是你要我做的嘛
What? What you wanted me to.
不过 保险起见问一句 你在做什么?
But just for argument's sake, what are you doing?
我想逃出去
l am trying to escape.
对...逃出去 我刚才就是想
Yeah, escape, that's where l was going
逃出去来着
with that thing l just did.
等等 等等 你是不是真以为我会跟你接吻?
Wait, wait. Did you actually think we were going to kiss?
- 没没没没没!  - 我们才刚刚见面!
No! lt's not what you think. We just met.
哦 天呐!
Oh, my.
我觉得它们需要点帮助
l think they need a little help.
我是说 我知道我很帅
l know how my feathers look,
但我可不是花花公子
but l am not that kind of bird.
# 说你 说我 #
Say you, say me
好吧 这出可不是我整的
Okay, l had nothing to do with that.
不过 这首歌真是不错啊
But, you have to admit it's actually a pretty good song.
# 情不自禁... #
Naturally
对啦 唱吧 莱昂内尔(歌曲原唱)
Yeah, sing it, Lionel.
(BLU EXCLAIMING)
哇哦 发展够迅速的
Wow. That was fast.
莱昂内尔·里奇的歌 屡试不爽
Lionel Richie works every time.
咱们还是给它们留点私人空间吧
We should probably give them some privacy.
我不太放心把布鲁自己留在这
l'm not so sure l should leave Blu here alone.
哦 没事 没事 没事 不用担心
No, don't worry.
索维欧会整晚盯着它们的
Sylvio will keep an eye on them all night.
再说 他已经有珠儿了
Besides, he's got Jewel.
(BLU SQUAWKING)
救命!
Help me!
(RJ CHATTERING ON RADIO)
现在是狂欢节最后一次倒计时!
This is the final countdown to Carnaval!
一起跳桑巴吧
Let's samba!
(SAMBA MUSIC PLAYING)
(WHOOPS)
(METAL CLATTERING)
哦...
Oh...
过来吧 可怜的小鸟乖乖
Come here, poor little birdie.
没事的 有我呢
lt's okay, l got you.
有我呢
l got you.
(MUFFLED)
(METAL CLINKING)
(MOANING)
不好意思!
Excuse me.
拜托 我想睡觉啊
Please, l am trying to sleep.
对不起哦 瞌睡虫 我想逃跑呢
l'm sorry, sleepy-head, l'm trying to escape.
逃跑 为什么啊? 这笼子多棒啊
Escape? Why? This cage is awesome.
这笼子...?
This... (LAUGHS)
哦 我想什么呢?
Oh, what was l thinking?
我可不指望一只宠物理解我
l wouldn't expect a pet to understand.
宠物? 你刚才叫我宠物?
Pet? Did you just call me a pet?
声明一下 我不是宠物
For the record, l am not a pet.
我是人类的伙伴
l am a companion.
还有 告诉你 随便你咋办
And you know what? Do whatever you want
反正明天一早琳达就会来接我
'cause tomorrow morning, Linda will come for me
这场噩梦就会彻底结束了
and this whole nightmare will be over.
真难以置信
lncredible!
你宁愿跟... 跟人类在一起也不愿跟自己的同类相处
You would rather be with a human than with your own kind.
嗯 那个人类这15年来一直给我
Well, that human has given me love and affection
爱心和关怀
for the past 15 years
而我的同类见到我15秒之后就想掐死我
whereas my own kind try to strangle me after 15 seconds.
对 正是因为他们 我才失去了一切
Yeah, well, because of them, l've lost everything.
你不能信任他们!
You can't trust them.
你当然...
BLU: Of course...
可以信任人类
you can trust humans.
(JEWEL GRUNTS)
珠儿?珠儿?
Jewel? Jewel?
你好啊!
Hi, there.
很高兴能和你共进晚餐
TULIO: lt was nice of you to join me for dinner.
我通常都是一个人进餐
I often eat alone.
当然 是我这份工作的原因
Because, of course, my work.
在认识你之前 我以为我才是"鸟痴"
l thought l was the bird nut until l met you.
嗯 对啊
Yes, right.
你有没有最喜欢的鸟?
Do you have a favorite bird?
嗯 很显然我是蓝色金刚鹦鹉铁杆粉丝
Well, obviously, l'm a blue macaw kind of gal.
确实，这种鸟类十分美丽
That makes sense. They are very handsome birds.
其实 吸引我的是它们的智力
Actually, it's the brains l'm more attracted to.
我对华丽的羽毛不是很感兴趣
l'm not so impressed by fancy feathers.
我完全明白你的意思
l know exactly what you mean.
我最喜欢的鸟是斑点猫头鹰
My favorite bird is the spotted owl.
我一直为那双
l've always been mesmerized
大大的
by those big...
圆而智慧的眼睛而着迷不已
round, intelligent eyes.
(LAUGHING LOUDLY)
(SCREAMS)
鸡心?
Chicken hearts?
熏眼睛了！噢！天啊！
Chicken eyes! Oh, gosh.
(EXCLAIMS)
噢...
Oh...
(ROOSTER CROWING)
噢
Oh.
喂
Hello?
(CHATTER ON POLICE RADIO)
(SOBBING)
哦 布鲁
Oh, Blu.
我们就不该离开布鲁的笼子
We should have never left Moose Lake.
都是我的错
This is all my fault.
不 琳达 别这样
No, no, Linda, Linda, please.
这不是你的错
This is not your fault.
你说得对
You're right.
不是我的错
lt's not my fault.
- 是你的错!  - 什么?
- lt's your fault! - What?
你用你的花言鸟语
With your little bird talk.
还有什么"拯救物种"
And that whole "save the species."
你知道吗？
Well, you know what?
就是你叽里呱啦的
Squawk, squawkity, squawk, squawk!
对不起，希望我说的不是脏话
l'm sorry. l didn't mean to curse.
我想不通!
l don't understand.
索维欧是业内最好的守卫了
Sylvio is the best guard in the business.
让我先搞清楚
So, let me get this straight.
你被一只白色的小鸟袭击了？
You were attacked by a little white bird?
没错 用这块布
Yes, with this rag.
捂住了我的嘴 像这样
He held it to my mouth like this.
(MUMBLING)
(SNIFFING)
我们完蛋了
We're doomed.
好吧 这一点也不像家
Okay. There's no place like home,
一点也不像
there's no place like home.
我真想回到自己的笼子啊
How l wish l was back in my own cage
那里有我的镜子 秋千还有小铃铛
with my mirror and my swing, and my little bell.
真怀念我的小铃铛
How l miss my little bell.
嘘 装死
Play dead.
啥? 我不需要装
What? l don't need to play dead,
我都快突发心脏病了
l'm about to have a heart attack.
照做就是了!
Just do it!
好吧
Fine.
(DRAMATIC GROAN)
(TWITCHING)
别抽搐了
Stop twitching.
拜托 有抽搐才逼真
Come on, it's the twitching that sells it.
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
进来吧 小子
Come on in, kid.
嗯 知道吗?
Well, what do you know?
干得不错啊 费尔南多
Good work, Fernando.
看到没 小子们？
You see, boys?
我以前怎么和你说我们这一行的？
What did l tell you about this one?
只付给他之前商量好的一半价钱吗？
That you were going to pay him half as much as you said?
错 你个白痴
No, you idiot.
他让我想起来我和他一样年纪的时候
That he reminds me of myself when l was that age.
机灵，有头脑
Smart, resourceful.
拿去吧 小子
Here you go, kid.
嘿 这还真是你答应给的一半啊
Hey. This is only half of what you promised me.
啊 闭嘴吧 小子
Ah, shut up, kid.
怎么...?
What the...
我肯定告诉过你，这些鸟要活的
l thought l told you l needed these birds alive.
告诉我 费尔南多
Tell me, Fernando...
这看起来像是活的吗?
does this look alive to you?
(EXCLAIMING)
抓住它!
Get her!
在那!
Come over here!
珠儿!
Jewel!
来这！
Come here!
(PANTING)
你好啊
Hello...
漂亮的小鸟
pretty bird.
怎么了?
What's the matter?
鹦鹉掐到你喉咙了?
Cockatoo got your throat?
奈杰！
Nigel!
要活的
Alive.
还没完哦
To be continued.
(GROANING)
这就是你的计划! 扔下我自己飞走! 天 谢谢你
That was your plan? To take off and leave me? Gee, thanks.
你为什么不跟着我?
Well, why didn't you follow me?
呃
Uh...
干得漂亮 奈杰
Nice work, Nigel.
是啊 干得漂亮 奈杰
Yeah, nice work, Nigel.
世上仅存的两只小蓝金刚鹦鹉
The last blue macaws on earth.
这可值不少钱呢
These are worth a fortune.
嘿 费尔南多! 把这个挂到隔壁去
Hey, Fernando, hang these up in the other room.
(BIRDS CALLING)
嘿！鸟哥们儿
Hey, birdie!
放我出去! 放我出去!　让我离开这!
Let me out! Let me out! Let me out of here!
谁是漂漂鸟？我是一只漂漂鸟
Who's a pretty bird? l'm a pretty bird.
漂漂鸟 漂漂鸟 我是一只漂漂鸟!
Pretty bird, l'm a pretty bird. l'm a pretty bird.
我是被冤枉的 他们抓错人了
l was framed. They got the wrong guy.
抱歉了伙计 我也是身不由己
Sorry, guys. Nothing personal.
那么，它们今后会怎样？
So, what's going to happen to them?
别担心 我们会给他们找到合适的家的
Don't worry, we're going to find good homes for them.
现在回家找妈妈去吧
Now go home to your mama.
但是我没有妈妈
But l don't have a mama.
爸爸呢?
Father?
兄弟?　金鱼呢？
Brother? Goldfish?
咱能把他留这吗 老大?
Can we keep him, boss?
不行!
No.
接下来那些小鸟会怎样啊？
So, Marcel, what's really going to happen to those birds?
挨冷受饿或被吃掉，谁在乎啊？
Plucked, stuffed, eaten, who cares?
我只知道 咱们要发财了
All l know is we're going to be rich.
咱们要发财了
We're gonna be rich!
快来 快来 比赛要开始了
Come on, come on! The game is starting!
是 你说得很清楚了 明天交货 否则免谈
Yes, you were very clear. Tomorrow or the deal is off.
当然，我有一对蓝金刚鹦鹉
Of course l have both the macaws.
对 我会亲自把它们运过去
Yes, l will deliver them myself.
(BIDDING FAREWELL lN FRENCH)
好了 你俩听着
All right, you two...
我们今晚装车
you load the truck tonight.
明早第一件事
And first thing in the morning,
就是带鸟儿们去机场
we bring those birds to the airport.
明白没?
You got it?
- 嗯 是 是  - 听到啦
Yeah, sure. All right. Heard you.
还有 你俩其中一个 来喂奈杰
And one of you, feed Nigel.
(BOTH GULPING)
剪刀 石头 布
Rock, paper, scissors, shoot!
耶!
Yes!
唔... 不对 剪刀剪掉石头
Nuh-uh,scissors cuts rock.
不是吧 怎么每次都是你赢?
Oh, man. How come you always win?
可爱的小鸟
Nice birdie.
(WHIMPERING)
拿去吧
Here you go.
(EXCLAIMS)
(GASPS)
(SIGHING)
食肉动物
Cannibal.
好吧 要淡定 关键是别慌
Okay, pull it together. The key is not to panic.
我没慌
l'm not panicking.
我没跟你说话 我自言自语来着
l wasn't talking to you, l was talking to me.
不过没关系 现在起 琳达随时会找到我们
But it's okay, because any minute now, Linda will find us.
哦 太好了 然后她会把我们装进另一个囚牢里是吧?
Great. And then she'll stick us behind another set of bars, right?
对 我是说 不对!
Yeah. l mean, no.
听着 宠物笼可能对你胃口
Look, pet, cages might work for you,
但我不想属于任何人
but l don't want to belong to anyone.
(RATTLING)
(ALL GASPING)
(SMACKING BEAK)
好像有什么卡在我的嘴里了
Something seems to be lodged in my beak.
帮个忙呗?
Would you mind?
(WHIMPERING)
(CACKLING)
哦 我知道我不是漂漂的小鸟
l know l'm not a pretty birdie...
不过我也曾经帅过
but l used to be quite a looker.
巨星
A star.
灯光 摄像 开始
Lights, camera, action.
“我曾柔温可人、野心上进”
l was striking, suave, ambitious.
“从爪到喙
Feet to beak...
如此可亲动人”
so birdie-licious
“现在我卑鄙，流氓 邪恶 ”
Now l'm vile, l am villainous, and vicious
“噢，还很阴毒”
OL, and malicious
“我也曾经，电视作秀、莺歌燕舞”
l had it all  A TV show, women, too
“我曾高大，足足一尺二”
l was tall Over one-foot-two
“而后一只长尾鹦鹉让我下了岗”
Then they got a pretty parakeet to fill my shoes
“于是我变得如此邪恶而无恶不作”
（明星葵花鹦鹉被炒）
That's why l am so evil, why l do what l do.
“他是位超级明星”
CHORUS: He was a super star
（如此年轻而举足轻重）
So young and vital
“他是如此的卑劣”
He's nasty
（一南美的年轻偶像）
A South American ldol
“他又如此的多疑”
He's a suspicious bird
（又是谁在说我坏话）
Who said that about me?
“他是如此的险恶”
A very vicious bird l'll have you rotisseried
（我把你们都烤了吃）
l'm a feathery freak With a beak
“我是一个长毛嘴叼的混蛋，一个鸟类杀手”
A bird murderer
“觉得你要比我给力？怎么没听过你名号？”
You think you're badder than me? l never heard of ya
“我很邪恶，会在你的奶酪里暗加毒虫”
l'm evil, l'll fill your cheese balls with weevils
“我向人类头顶拉稀，然后说是海鸥干的”
l poop on people and l blame it on seagulls
是他干的
lt was him.
“他是只卑鄙的鸟（我无可匹敌）”
He's a nasty bird l'm invincible
“他十分苍白可怖（我无人能挡）”
He's ghastly l'm un-mince-able
“我又是阴魂不散，无法摆脱”
l'm unwashable, unrinseable
“就像法外之徒，我无法无天”
Like an abandoned school l have no principle
“听好了，所有巴西的鸟儿”
All of you Brazilian birds
“1800万的鸟儿们”
All 18 million birds
“告诉你们我要怎么做吧”
l'll tell you what l'm going to do
“我要让你们都…”
l'm going to make you
(BIRDS VOCALIZING)
闭嘴，都给我闭嘴
Shut up, now. Shut up!
(SILENCE)
除了我
lt's just me.
“我会让你们都变得…”
l will make you ugly...
“一样丑陋”
...too.
嘿!
BLU: Hey!
祝你恶梦
Sweet nightmares.
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
不给力啊老兄
Not cool, man!
很吓人，但很不给力
Scary, but not cool!
嘿 你还好吧?
Hey, are you okay?
不 我一点都不好!
No, l am definitely not okay!
等等! 你在做什么?
Wait. What are you doing?
逃跑啊
Getting out of here.
你要来帮忙吗 还是怎样?
Are you going to help me or what?
事实上 求生手册上是这么说的
Actually, all the survival guides
静坐着等待 然后...救援就会来
say to sit and wait, and help will come.
没人会来!
No one is coming!
我们只有靠自己 如果静坐 只能等死!
We are on our own and if we just sit here, we're going to die!
(METAL CLANKING)
好球 好球
Yes! Yes!
好球
Yes!
不！
No!
奈杰 快闪开
ARMANDO: Nigel! Get out of the way!
等等
Hold on!
停下 停下 直接开门不就好了吗?
Stop! Stop! Why don't you just open the door?
你在耍我吗?
Are you kidding me?
怎么? 这只是个普通的门闩而已 只要...
What? lt's just a standard flip slide bolt.
快来！飞！
Come on! Let's fly!
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
- 呃 我不会... - 什么？你不会什么？
l can't. What? You can't what?
(BLU GASPS)
我不会飞
l can't fly!
(JEWEL SCREAMING)
你就不能早点告诉我吗!
You couldn't tell me this before now?
之前没这必要啊
lt didn't matter before now!
我恨你
l hate you.
(SCREAMING)
还有什么是我该知道的吗?
ls there anything else l need to know?
有，我不会飞，我会挖鼻孔
Yes, l can't fly, l pick my beak,
时不时我还会在洗澡时尿尿
and once in a while l pee in the bird-bath.
满意没?
Happy?
他们在那儿!
There they are!
我们得赶快离开这儿!
We got to get out of here!
走！快！
Just move! Move!
等等 等等 听我说
Wait, wait.Listen to me.
或许飞行不是我的特长 但是步行我拿手
Flying may not be my thing, but walking is.
跟着我的口令 左脚前 右脚后
Follow my lead.lnside leg, outside leg.
好耶 我明白了
Yeah, okay,l got it.
内脚、外脚、内脚、外脚…
lnside, outside,inside, outside!
好球 好球!
Yes! Yes! Yes!
- 好球 好球!  - 来吧!
Yes. Yes!Come on!
(MIMICKING DOG)
(CAT SCREECHING)
看见没 我还精通外语
See? l'm bilingual, too!
(NIGEL SQUAWKING HARSHLY)
这下好了
This is great!
我和世界上唯一不会飞的那只鸟锁一块儿了!
l'm chained to the only bird in the world who can't fly!
事实上 世界上有40种不会飞的鸟类
Actually, there are about 40 species of flightless birds.
- 低头!(鸭子!)  - 不对哦 鸭子会飞!
- Duck! - No, ducks can fly.
不! 我叫你低头!
No! Duck!
(BOTH EXCLAIMING)
耶!
Yay!
(BOTH SCREAMING)
好球!
Yes!
(COMMENTATOR
SPEAKING PORTUGUESE)
很好!
Yes!
小心!
Hold on!
不!
No!
不！
(CLUCKING)
(NIGEL GROANING)
给我滚开，你们这些讨厌的家禽
Get out of here, you putrid poultry!
(EXCLAIMING)
(CHAIN CLINKING)
(TWIG SNAPPING)
那是什么?
What was that?
一根棍子
A stick.
啊 那个呢?
And that?
一块石头而已
lt's just a rock.
好吧 耶
Right. Yeah.
(SHUDDERING)
我背上是不是有只蜘蛛?
ls that a spider on my back?
你有完没完
Will you quit it?
只是片树叶 转过来
lt's just a leaf. Turn around.
叶子嘛，我就说
Leaf. Told you.
来吧 我们得找个安全的地方过夜
Now, come on, we need to find a safe place to spend the night.
安全? 安全!
Safe? Safe?
我们在丛林里!
We are in the jungle.
你知道人类是怎样形容丛林的吗？
You know when people say, "lt's a jungle out there"?
我敢肯定不会是什么好词
Well, l'm pretty sure they don't mean it as a good thing.
听着，我也不想打断你话头
Look, l hate to break it to you,
但这里才是我们种族原本生活的地方
but this is where our kind naturally lives.
嘿 别拿自然忽悠我
Hey, don't talk to me about nature.
我可有看动物星球频道
l watch Animal Planet.
我了解所有的食物链
l know all about the food chain.
看见没 看见没 在这儿我就是碟开胃菜
You see? Out here, l'm just an hors d'oeuvre.
顶多算一盘带羽毛的春卷
Nothing more than a feathery spring roll.
这就是为什么我们要呆在树上 而不是地上
That is why we stay in the trees and not on the ground.
你先上
After you.
哦 不 我不这么认为
No, l don't think so.
呃 不 还是给我个人造小屋什么的
Nuh-uh. No. l would feel much more comfortable
我更有安全感
in something man-made.
嘿 那上面怎么样?
Hey, how about up there?
真不敢相信 我得拖着你愚蠢的大屁股上去
l can't believe l have to drag your clumsy butt up there.
拖着我?
Drag me? (SCOFFS)
看好学着点
Watch and learn.
噢
Oh!
布鲁!  等等啊!
Blu! Just wait one...
布鲁？
Blu?
现在是谁拖着谁的大屁股呢 哈?
Who's dragging whose butt now?
哈哈 很幽默
Ha ha. Very funny.
(LAUGHING)
看到没 谁要会飞啊?
You see? Who needs flying?
鸟啊 鸟类要会飞
Birds. Birds need flying.
飞行意味着...
Flying is...
意味着自由 不用依赖别人
lt's freedom and not having to rely on anyone.
你难道不想吗?
Don't you want that?
我不知道 听起来有点寂寞
l don't know. lt sounds a little lonely.
睡会儿吧
Let's get some sleep.
我可能暂时先不睡
l'm probably going to be up for a little while.
因为我生物钟还在明尼苏达州呢
Because l'm still on Minnesota time.
晚安
Good night.
晚安 珠儿
Good night, Jewel.
晚安 琳达
Good night, Linda.
打扰了 先生
Excuse me, sir?
你见过我的鸟吗?
Have you seen my bird?
你... 你见过我的鸟吗?
呃
Mmm-mmm.
(SIGHING)
不好意思 呃 请问你见过我的鸟吗?
Excuse me? Have you seen my bird?
(SNORING)
你见过我的鸟吗? 蓝色的羽毛
Have you seen my bird? Blue feather.
小姐 美国来的小姐
Lady! American lady!
(GASPS)
布鲁? 在哪儿？
Blu? Where?
(EXCLAIMING)
(GASPS)
哇 我知道你的鸟在哪儿
Wow. l know where your birds are.
你找到布鲁了? 你确定?
You found Blu? Are you sure?
这是他的
lt's his!
让我看看
Let me see that.
(VOCALIZING)
没错
You're right.
好吧 他在哪儿?
Okay. Where is he?
来吧 我们走 我带你去找他
Come on, let's go! l'll take you to him.
不 不 不 琳达 等等
No, no. Linda, wait.
我们不认识这孩子 我们不能相信他
We don't know this boy. We can't trust him.
我必须得相信他
l have to trust him.
我没有其他选择
l don't have a choice.
(CLUCKING)
(CLEARING THROAT)
你们把我当白痴吗?
Do you think l'm an idiot?
他们是两只鸟 不仅锁在一起 还被关在笼子里
They were two birds chained together in a cage.
这样你们都能把他们弄丢?
How could you lose them?
老大 他们比我们还聪明
They outsmarted us, boss.
不过别担心 我们会把它们抓回来的
But don't worry, we'll get them back.
我有个计划
l have a plan.
那好 你准备怎么做?
Great. What are you going to do?
在城里大喊“小鸟快来啊，小鸟快来啊”？
Wander the city calling "Here birdie, birdie. Here birdie"?
照你这口气 不管什么方法听起来都傻透了
Well, anything sounds dumb when you say it like that.
(SNICKERING)
今晚之前 我们必须带着那些鸟到达机场
Okay. We have to get the birds to the airport tonight.
但今天是狂欢节 游行队伍会封死道路啊
But it's Carnaval. All the roads will be blocked by the parade.
所以我本打算今早出发的!
And that's why l wanted to go this morning.
奈杰!
Nigel.
这只鸟比你们俩加在一块还要聪明十倍
This bird is 10 times smarter than the two of you combined.
是啊是啊 那如果他真这么聪明
Yeah, well, if he's so smart,
你怎么不让他负责这事儿?
then why don't you put him in charge?
我正打算让他负责
l am putting him in charge.
别再提建议了!
Stop suggesting things.
去找到他们 奈杰
Go find them, Nigel.
(KIDS CHEERING)
嗯
Hmm.
如果我们无法穿过游行队伍
lf we can't get through the parade,
干脆加入好了
we'll have to be in the parade.
哈?
Huh?
(GRUNTING)
你确定这管用吗?
Are you sure this is going to work?
必须的 看我的分析图
Positive. Check out my math.
是啊 这... 这让我很欣慰 多谢
Yeah, that's comforting. Thank you.
听着 我们得把铁链解开
Look, let's just get this chain broken.
没错 然后我们就可以去找琳达了
Right. Then we can go and find Linda.
不对 是你就可以去找琳达了
No, you can go find Linda.
一旦这铁链解开了
Once this chain is off,
我就会重返自由回到丛林的怀抱 一言为定?
l'm going to go back to being free in the jungle. Deal?
好 一言为定
Fine. Deal.
干得漂亮 科学狂鸟
Nice try, brainiac.
(LEAVES RUSTLING)
我觉得有东西在盯着我们
l think something is watching us.
(CHEEPING)
小心哦，布鲁，他们可能会把你抱死哦
Be careful, Blu. They might snuggle you to death.
过来
Come here.
哦
Ow!
入侵者！
lntruders!
切吧！
Cut it out!
停
Now stop...
(SCREAMING)
不！别！
No! Don't!
攻击!
Attack!
(BOTH SCREAMING)
救命！
BLU: Help!
下面在闹什么呢?
What's going on down there?
走开，快走开
Go, go. Off with you.
爸爸！爸爸！爸爸！
Daddy! Daddy! Daddy!
好啦 孩子们 孩子们 跟你们说了上千次了
l've told you a thousand times.
曼纽尔 索非亚 听我说
Manoela, Sofia, come on now, listen to me.
嗷! 很好 戳到眼睛啦
Oh, yeah, right in the eye.
哦 太可爱了 不是吗?
Precious, aren't they?
我的孩子! 17个啦 还有个就快出生了
Kids? Seventeen of them and one on the way.
嘿... 你们 放下! 别晃他们
Hey! He's not a maraca, stop shaking him!
拜他们所赐 我羽毛都不剩多少了
They're giving me gray feathers.
哦 爸爸要休息会儿啦
This papa needs a break.
这么看来 你们小情侣是要去狂欢节?
So, you two lovebirds headed for Carnaval?
哇 情侣?
Whoa! Lovebirds?
我们顶多算熟人
We're more like acquaintance-birds.
连熟人都算不上 我们更像是"被锁在一起" 仅此而已
Not even that, we're more like chained-to-each-other birds.
没错 我是说... 嗷!
Yeah. l mean, if... Ow!
这些孩子怎么总跟羽毛过不去?
What is it with this kid and the feathers?
我们也不知道 我们准备带他们去做检查
We have no idea. We're having him tested.
那你可以帮我们把这玩意儿弄下来吗?
So, do you think you could help us get this thing off?
你们真幸运 你们认识了拉斐尔
Lucky for you, you know Rafael,
拉斐尔人脉奇广
and Rafael knows everyone.
噢! 又戳到眼睛啦! 好吧 你们是要我叫妈妈来啦!
Again with the eye. Okay, want me to call your mother?
不要!
No!
很次都奏效 他们可害怕她了
Works every time. They're scared to death of her.
叫我来干什么?
Call me for what?
伊娃 亲爱的
Eva, my love...
我要带这对小情侣去见路易兹
l must take this young couple to see Luiz.
路易兹?
Luiz!
你可骗不了我
You don't fool me for a second.
你和你的朋友只是想偷偷溜去狂欢节吧
You and your amigo just want to sneak off to Carnaval.
哦 狂欢节
Carnaval.
在那神奇的时刻 我遇见了世界上最美的小鸟
That magical time when l met the most beautiful bird in the world.
Oh! Ugh.
我还记得我第一次见你时 放的那首歌
l still remember the song that was playing when l first laid eyes on you.
“高挑性感、年轻动人”
Tall and tan and young and lovely
“来自伊帕内马的女孩正向我走来”
The girl from lpanema goes walking
来吧，宝贝，唱啊！
Come on, baby, sing it!
“当她走过人群，人们都为这美丽惊呼”
And when she passes, each one she passes goes, ah!
(BIRDS SQUAWKING)
如同最甜美的河流细细流淌
Like a river of the sweetest honey.
我想爱情也能让人耳聋
Oh. l guess love is deaf, too.
快过来
Come here.
ALL: Eww.
好吧 带他们去找路易兹 但要早点回来哦
Okay. Take them to Luiz, but hurry back.
你就像个天使
You are an angel.
我会想你的 我鲜嫩多汁的小芒果
l'll miss you my juicy little mango.
我也是，我亲爱的甜木瓜
l'll miss you my pudgy papaya.
(KIDS SHOUTING)
嘿! 帕高 卡洛斯! 把你们的弟弟放下 立刻!
Hey! Marco! Carlos! Put your brother down, now!
真不敢相信 她真的放我走了
l can't believe she actually let me go.
那个路易兹那儿离这儿有多远?
So, how far is this Luiz?
不远 直线飞过去30分钟吧
Not far. Thirty minutes as the crow flies.
那金刚鹦鹉走过去要多久?
And how long as the macaw walks?
这小子不会飞
Bobo here can't fly.
但他是只鸟啊
But he's a bird.
并不是所有的鸟都会飞
Not all birds fly.
鸵鸟就不会...
There are ostriches...
你又不是鸵鸟
You're not an ostrich.
呃 理论上说不是而已 等等
Not technically, but... Wait.
朋友们 我想帮你们 可是要全程步行
My friends, l want to help, but to walk the whole way...
这根本不可能!
lt can't be done!
爸爸在哪儿?
KID: Where's Daddy?
爸爸 爸爸! 快来 回到你的房间
Daddy? Daddy? Come over here. Go back to your room.
但 嘿
But, hey.
我们试试看说不定能行呢，快点走吧
We might as well give it a shot. Let's go quickly.
不不，不要回头，他们能感到你的恐惧
No, don't look back. They sense fear.
(SCREECHING)
多可爱的猴子啊
What an adorable monkey.
(PEOPLE LAUGHING)
(CALLING)
(BLOWING RASPBERRY)
嘿 我的手表!
Hey! My watch!
孩子们 你们好啊
Hello, boys.
看来你们这一天很忙碌啊
Seems like you've had a busy day.
哦 怎么? 这个吗?
What? This?
这只是我们找到的一些东西
This is just some stuff we found.
对吧 小子们?
Right, boys?
是 是的
Yeah. Yeah.
我对你们这些小勾当没兴趣
l'm not interested in your nicked knick-knacks.
你们这样的盗窃方法可闷死我了
Your burgled baubles bore me.
有两只蓝色的金刚鹦鹉不见了
There are two blue macaws out there
我需要你和你的手下来帮我找到他们
and l need your multitude of eyes to help me find them.
哦 是啊 那我们有什么好处?
Oh, yeah? What's in it for us?
问得好
Well, that's a fair question.
(SCREAMING)
我们来商量商量
Let's discuss it.
很显然 我明白你的意思
l certainly see your point,
但我能用什么来回报你呢?
but what could l possibly do for you in return?
救我 救我!
Save me! Save me!
哦 这想法不错啊
Well, that's a thought. Yeah.
就这样? 我可不想让你觉得我是在骗你
But is it enough? l don't want to feel like l'm cheating you.
救我 救我!
Help me! Help me! No, no!
我们会照办的 我们会照办的 求你 救我
We'll do it, we'll do it. Save me, please.
救救我
Save me!
好吧 我有出手救你
All right, you've twisted my wing.
成交
Deal.
现在 还有问题吗?
Now then? Any more questions?
没有？好
No? Good.
你们分头行动 天黑之前
You will spread out and you will find these macaws
找到这两只金刚鹦鹉
by the end of the day
不然 就让你们每人感受一下从天而降的乐趣!
or it's flying lessons for everyone!
快去!
Go!
(ALL HOOTING)
做好你们的事
Go do your monkey business.
(WHIMPERING)
我改主意了
l've changed my mind, yeah.
不如我们去看看公车时刻表什么的吧
Maybe we can find a bus schedule or something.
不是吧你 你不会退缩了吧?
Come on, you're not going to back out now.
在女士面前可不能退缩
Not in front of the lady.
好吧 好... 好的
Okay, yeah. Yeah, sure.
好了 就是要这样的态度
All right, that's the spirit.
你确定你要飞?
You're sure you're up for this?
当然 当然 我是说
Yeah, yeah. l mean,
反正这又不是从高山或其他什么的
it's not like we're just hurling ourselves
上面掉下来
off a mountain or something.
对吗?
Right?
事实上，我的确打算这么做
Actually that was pretty much my entire plan.
啥？
What?
别担心 布鲁 你天生会飞的
Don't worry, Blu, it's in your DNA.
而且 我们这位没毛的朋友都会飞 你怎么可能做不到呢?
And if our featherless friends can do it, how hard can it be?
等等 停下，救命啊！
MAN: Wait, wait!
(SCREAMING)
Mommy!
好玩吧?
Fun, right?
是啊 很有趣
Yeah. Fun.
好了 现在你俩靠近点
Okay. l need you two to get closer.
再近点
Closer.
要更近
很好
Nice.
现在用翅膀围着对方
Now put your wings around each other.
什么? 来吧，老兄
What? Come on, amigo!
她又不会咬你
lt's not like she's going to bite!
你不会吧？
Will you?
你试试就知道了
We'll see.
现在
Now,
你扇右翅膀
you flap your right wing,
你扇左翅膀 然后一起用力 你们就飞起来了
you flap your left wing, and together you fly.
这根本不符合空气动力学啊
But this doesn't seem aerodynamically possible.
你想太多了
You think too much.
飞翔不是靠想象
Flying is not what you think up here,
而是靠你去感受
it's what you feel in here.
当你感受到自己的心跳时
And when you feel the rhythm of your heart,
就像是跳桑巴
it's like samba.
你自然而然就飞起来了
You fly!
(WHOOPING)
看吧 就这么简单
See? lt's easy!
简单?
Easy?
简单？对你而言是
Easy for you to say, because from here
我觉得难死了
it looks really, really hard.
嘿 如果你还想见到琳达
Hey, if you want to see Linda again,
就只有这么做了
this is the only way.
好吧 你是对的
Okay. You're right.
当然 为琳达而飞
Yes, l am. This is for Linda.
没错 放轻松
Right. Keep it simple.
轻轻呼吸 坚定 抬起 起飞...
Easy breezy. Thrust, lift, drag...
别啰嗦 我们飞! 等等!
Come on! Let's go! Wait!
内脚、外脚、内脚、外脚…
lnside, outside, inside, outside.
加油 布鲁 你能做到的!
Come on, Blu! You can do it!
我能做到 我能做到...
BLU: l can do it. l can do it.
我能做到!
l can do it.
我做不到！
l can't do it!
又来了!
Not again!
(BOTH SCREAMING)
我还活着吗? 当然
Am l dead? No!
我们还活着!
We're still alive!
(WHOOPING)
(MAS QUE NADA PLAYING)
这真不可思议
Wow! This is incredible.
哇噢
Wow.
我从没见过这么美的景色
This is the most beautiful thing l've ever seen.
知道你错过多少美景了吧?
See what you've been missing?
是啊
Yeah.
好了 布鲁 你在飞呢
All right, Blu, you're flying!
算飞吧 虽然不是真的飞 但你感觉到了吗?
Sort of. Not really, but do you feel it?
是的
Yes!
我感觉到了
l do feel it.
不 不要 布鲁! 等下！
No, no, Blu! Wait!
(EXCLAIMING lN PORTUGUESE)
(BOTH SCREAMING)
(SCREAMING)
对不起 对不起 对不起!
Sorry, sorry, sorry.
我们要死了!
We're gonna die!
(ALL SCREAMING)
你没有用心感受
You did not feel it in here.
你说呢？
You think?
(TRUCK ENGINE STARING)
我们还是搭车去找路易兹吧
Let's catch a ride to Luiz.
快点啊 你们两个笨蛋!
Hurry, you two!
(SPEAKING PORTUGUESE)
好的
Okay.
Last of the species here.
快走
Move it!
等等，等等我
Hey. Wait up.
快点啊 小情侣
Come on, lovebirds!
你做到了
You made it.
真希望我能安安全全地连飞五分钟
l would love to go five minutes without almost getting killed.
我要求是不是太多了?
ls that too much to ask?
对于一只不会飞的鸟来说 是太多了
For a bird who can't fly, oh, yeah.
(WHISTLING)
他们开始为狂欢节而戒严了
They're starting to close off the streets for Carnaval.
希望你是对的 我们没什么时间了
You better be right, kid. Because we're running out of time.
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
(HONKING)
我们的车子根本开不过去
l'll never be able to get my car through this crowd.
别担心，放着我来
Don't worry, l'm on it.
(EXCLAIMING)
Watch it!
嘿 小子 哪来的摩托车?
Hey, kid, how did you get this bike?
- 拿你的吉普车换的  - 什么?
- l traded it for your Jeep. - What?
咋了？这车保养得很棒
Yeah, it's in great condition.
呃…保养得还行
Well, good condition!
嘿 让开点!
Hey! Out of the way!
小心!
Look out!
抓好!
Hold on!
(EXCLAIMING) Ow!
如果还是解不开
l'm going to chew through my own leg
我就咬断自己的腿
if this doesn't come off soon.
放轻松 我们已经到了 现在去找路易兹
Relax. lf l know Luiz, we're right where we want to be.
嘿 拉斐!
Hey! Rafi!
这不是狂欢节之王嘛
lf it isn't the king of Carnaval!
尼科 佩德罗! 大家都来了啊?
Nico! Pedro! What up, family?
小子 你之前藏哪儿了?
Where you been hiding yourself, bird?
还以为你挂了呢
Man, l thought you were dead.
暂停 倒带
Hold up! Rewind.
这不是笼子里那只鸟吗?
Ain't that the bird from the cage?
我觉得我们爱的教育很成功啊
l think our love lessons went down smooth.
进展真快呢
You work fast.
你小子本事到家了
Baby got beak.
你们连在一起 现在还飞得很起劲
You was locked up and now you're rolling with a hot-wing.
我真想像你一样
l want to be like you.
别 和你们想得不一样 我们是被锁一起了
No, it's not what you think.We're just chained together.
嘿 不是我说你
Hey, l'm not judging you.
在我们面前还装
Keep it spicy. Oh, yeah.
嘿 伙计们 我们在找路易兹 你看到他了吗?
Hey, guys, we're looking for Luiz. Have you seen him?
看到了 我看到他了 但你没看到
Yeah, l seen him, but you didn't,
你错过他了
because you just missed him.
他坐着电车回车库了
He took the trolley back to the garage.
太好了
Great.
放松点 小宝贝 你们可以乘下一趟
Relax, baby bird. You could catch the next one.
现在是时候谈谈下一阶段了
Yeah, it's time to take it to the next level.
这一阶段有问题吗？
What's wrong with this level?
拜托，现阶段根本不配称阶段
下阶段才了不起啦
Come on! This ain't the level. The next level's the level.
你应该摇摆你的尾巴
You got to shake your tail feathers.
我们得把锁链解开
We got to get this chain off first.
来嘛 小情侣 你们可是在里约呢 要玩的尽兴
Come on, lovebirds! You're in Rio! You should enjoy it!
是啊，享受人生
Yeah! Live a little.
(YELPS)
(VIBRATING)
(SIGHING)
(PHONE CHIMES)
(LAUGHING)
我们找到了
We got them.
(DANCE MUSIC PLAYING) BIRD: Hey!
欢迎来到天堂
Welcome to paradise!
气氛真好 哈?
Some party, huh?
这地方实在太酷了
This is the coolest place l've ever seen.
就是音响声音太大了
Despite all the obvious health code violations.
我喜欢你 虽然你说的都是废话
l like you! Nothing you say makes any sense.
好了 大家伙儿听着
All right, everyone, listen up!
拉斐给我们带来了外地来的特别来宾
Rafi has some special guests from out of town
让我们来展示下我们的热情
and let's show them some love,
貌似他们不经常出来旅游呢
because l don't think they get out much.
Yo, yo, yo.
大家都把翅膀举起来
Everybody put their wings together
尽你所能 大声鼓掌
and clap them as loud as you can.
拍手 拍手 用力点 大声拍手
Flap them. Clap them. l don't care, slap them.
(SQUAWKING)
这里是依帕内玛派对 宝贝
Party in the lpanema, baby.
“我要开派对 我要舞桑巴”
l wanna party l wanna samba
“我要开派对”
l wanna party
“享受人生”
And live my life My life
“我要开派对”
l wanna party Party
“展翅高飞”
And fly
“我要高飞，如同鸟儿一般”
High! l'm gonna fly Fly just like a bird
“但你是鸟儿啊”
But you are a bird
“是的没错”
OL, yeah, you're right
“让我高飞，如同火箭
So let me fly just like a rocket then
直上云霄”
Okay Fly so high
“直上云颠，直到兴奋缺氧而返航”
Where l need to come down for oxygen
“因为一旦我们开始飞翔，便无法停止”
'Cause once we start it Baby, ain't no, ain't no stopping then
“因为我想享受人生，尽情舞会”
'Cause l just want to live my life and party
“我想要的一切就是自由，起舞摇摆”
All l want is to be free And rock my body
PEDRO: Okay
“而后环游世界
NICO: l've been around the world
我要在里约享受人生”
And l want to live my life in Rio
“在里约，因为是里约，因为里约
真正的生活”
'Cause l Rio,
'cause l Rio realize
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
我不知道
l don't know.
跳得好 布鲁
All right, Blu!
飞吧！
And fly!
“我是桑巴舞大师，大师大师…”
l'm that samba, samba master Master, master, master, master
“我要对着我的音响引亢高歌，高歌…”
Push out sound from a ghetto blaster
Blaster, blaster,blaster, blaster
嘿 她喜欢你
Hey. She likes you.
你说什么呢? 你有在听吗？
What are you talking about? Haven't you been listening?
没，但我有在看
No, but l've been watching.
尽显自我吧，去吧
Just be yourself. Go on.
“我要舞桑巴”
l wanna samba Party
“我要开派对”
l wanna party Party
“我要舞桑巴”
l wanna samba Party
“我要开派对”
l wanna party Party
“享受人生”
And live my life My life
“我要开派对”
l want to party Party
“展翅高飞”
And fly
(ALL CHANTING)
(VOCALIZING)
(MUSIC STOPS)
(CONTINUES CHANTING)
你们俩跟我走吧
You two are coming with me.
做你的猴子梦吧
ln your little monkey dreams.
Yeah.
那是吐给你的
That was meant for you.
(CHUCKLING)
来嘛 我们不能好好相处吗?
Come on. Can we all just get along?
这不关你的事 大鼻鸟
This isn't your fight, big-nose.
你欺负我朋友 就是欺负我!
You mess with my friends, you mess with me!
就是欺负我们!
ALL: And us!
没错 小金刚
Yeah, little King Kong.
(MONKEY DRUMMING OMINOUSLY)
我是来打酱油的
l don't know what's going on here.
鸟猴大战!
Birds versus monkeys!
揍他们！
Get them!
做得好 伙计!
Yippee-kai-yay, monkey man!
Yee-haw! Giddy-up!
没中！
Missed!
(YELLING THREATENINGLY)
我们该走了
We got to go!
(GASPS)
搭顺风车吗？
Need a lift?
(GASPS)
接招吧 胆小鬼
Take that, you funky monkey!
(JEWEL WHOOPING)
- 谢谢!  - 不用谢!
Thank you! Anytime!
我说得没错吧
That's what l'm talking about!
伙计们 我们甩掉它们了!
Man, we threw down!
没错 我们甩掉了
Yeah, we threw down.
你们俩简直是炉火纯青
You guys were like fire and ice.
电闪雷鸣 天造地设
Thunder and lightning! Hip and hop!
七荤八素
Cheese and sprinkles!
嗯？
Huh?
那是我乡下土话
lt's a Minnesota thing.
看吧 你就是爱说废话
RAFAEL: You see? Nothing you say makes any sense.
(TULIO AND LINDA EXCLAIMING)
来吧 跟我来
Come on, follow me.
(BOTH MOANING)
怎么会这样?
What?
可是 鸟儿们本来在这儿的啊
But the birds were here.
是啊 由你说 小子
Yeah, sure they were, kid.
我发誓 鸟儿就在这里
l swear, the birds were right here.
你怎么知道?
Well, how do you know?
因为
Because
是...是我抓他们来的
l'm... l'm the one who took them.
是你？！
You!
我也不想伤害他们 我只是需要钱
l didn't want to hurt anybody, l needed the money.
费尔南多 我那么相信你
But Fernando, l trusted you!
我知道 但...
l know, but...
(MEN LAUGHING)
老天，真棒极了
Man, that's good.
嘿 你们回来啦
Hey, guys.
你怎么在这儿?
What are you doing here?
我只是想看看有没有活给我干
l just wanted to see if you had any work for me.
其实，如果你两小时前就来的话
Well, if you were here two hours ago,
就能帮我装箱…
you could've helped us load the... Ow!
- 怎么啦?  - 闭嘴!
What? Shut up.
那么 你们俩打扮好是要去参加狂欢节?
So, why are you guys dressed for Carnaval?
我们混在人海中偷渡小鸟 没人会注意到... 哦!
So no one will notice us when we smuggle these... Ow!
闭嘴!
Shut up!
我们要用彩车
We made a float.
哦 彩车啊!
Oh! A float!
你们俩都去参加 那我能去吗?
So you guys are going to the parade. Can l come?
我很会跳舞呢
l'm a great dancer.
他能一起吗? 求你了 拜托 多个人多把手
Can he come? Come on, please. Three is better than two.
好吧 但我们得快点
Fine. We got to hurry though.
哇哦 我差点忘了
Whoa! l almost forgot.
我放哪儿了? 我记得就在这里啊
Where did l put it? l thought it was right here.
在这里!
There it is.
找到了!
Got it.
走吧
Let's go.
快点 小子
ARMANDO: Hurry up, kid.
能让他和我们一起上飞机吗?
TIPA: Can he ride on the plane with us, too? Ow!
闭嘴
ARMANDO: Shut up!
我们不能让他们登上飞机
No. We can't let them get on that plane.
你会骑摩托车 对吧?
You can drive a motorcycle, right?
小菜一碟
You insult me.
(EXHALING)
不，我不会开摩托车
No, l can't drive a motorcycle.
(DISTORTED SCREAM)
这就跟滑雪橇一样
lt's just like riding a snowmobile.
(EXCLAIMS lN DISGUST)
怎么回事?
What happened?
爸爸?
Papa?
到底怎么回事?
What happened?
哦，不！ 放开我
Oh, no! Let me go.
别唧唧喳喳的 快回答我!
Stop your chirping and talk to me!
不 我什么都不知道
No, no. l don't know anything. Help!
我照着你的头一口咬下去
When l bite down on your head,
你会炸开还是碎掉呢？
will it go "pop," or will it go "crack"?
那两只不听话的鸟儿呢？
Where are the cerulean birds?
得说明一下 我说的是布鲁
That means blue, by the way.
他们逃走了 找路易兹去了
They escaped. Went to Luiz.
还有别的吗?
Anything else?
他们说你人很好
They said you were very nice.
是吗?
Did they?
说谎
Liar.
而且 还很帅?
And handsome, too.
就不该派猴子去办鸟事
Never send a monkey to do a bird's job.
Psst!
少担心，我能行
Don't worry. l got it.
这就对了，这才是好孩子
There he goes. That's my boy.
觉得热吗？觉得我都流汗了
ls it hot? l think l'm sweating.
虽然我记得这从生物学角度上看我是不可能流汗的
l didn't even think that was biologically possible, and yet, look.
哇喔
Wow.
是啊，你的好孩子，没错
Yeah, that's your boy, all right.
好吧，他的确需要帮助
Okay, so he needs a little help.
来吧 那我们就帮他一把
Come on, let's give him some.
营造气氛
Set the mood.
让我来吧
All right, look, l'm on it.
我最擅长营造气氛了 看我的
l know how to set the mood. Check it out.
# 来吧 来吧 来吧 来吧 姑娘 #
Get a, Get a, Get a Get a girl
# 快来 快来 快来 姑娘 #
Get, Get, Get Get a girl
# 拉她手 拉她手跳舞 #
Take her, take her to the floor
# 让她看 让她搂着你转 #
Show her, show her how you roll
# 弯腰 弯腰 弯下腰 #
Drop it, drop it, drop it low
# 弯腰 弯腰 弯弯腰 #
Drop it low, drop-drop it low
这是哪门子气氛？
What kind of mood is that?
佩德罗 佩德罗 你这个有点激动过头了
Pedro, Pedro, a little too aggressive.
我不是讨厌你的创意
l'm not hating on your creativity,
只不过我觉得这个更合适
but l think l got this one.
跟着我的拍子
Follow my lead.
(WHISTLING MELODICALLY)
这还比较靠谱
Now, that's more like it.
“没有认真细想，没有寻找…”
Wasn't really thinking Wasn't looking
“没有想要一个答案”
Wasn't searching for an answer
“在月光下”
ln the moonlight
“当我凝望你脸庞”
When l saw your face
哇！ 多美的夕阳啊
Wow! What a beautiful sunset.
是啊
Yeah.
喂! 布鲁
Psst! Blu.
- 我在这儿 - 告诉她 你有双美丽的眼睛
Down here. Just tell her, "You have beautiful eyes."
对 好主意
That's good. Great idea.
我有双美丽的眼睛
l have beautiful eyes.
对 是的 当然 你眼睛 挺好看的
Yeah, okay. Sure, they're nice.
不! 她的眼睛 是她的眼睛!
No, her eyes. Her eyes.
你的眼睛 是你的眼睛很美 不是我的
Right, yeah. Your eyes, your eyes are great, not mine.
我的意思是 我的眼睛是不错
l mean, mine are okay.
但是你的眼睛 我猜你能完全看透那双眼睛
But yours, l bet you can see right through them.
布鲁!
Blu!
告诉她你的感受
Just tell her how you feel.
- 珠儿  - 嗯?
Jewel. Yeah.
我一直想告诉你 我...
l've been wanting to tell you that l...
我... 咳!
That l...
(CHOKING)
你真逗 话都说不完整
How sweet. You're getting choked up.
你真呛住了! 好! 看我的!
Oh! You're choking! Okay! All right!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
JEWEL: Come on, Blu, move with me. Stay with me, Blu.
(STOPS SINGING)
One more, come on. One more time!
是啊 那就是我的好老弟
Yep, that's my boy.
(MIMICS FALLING BOMB)
女士们先生们 我已经把你们 带到路易兹的车库了
Ladies and gentlemen, l give you Luiz's garage.
- 你先请 - 不 不 你先
After you. No, no, you first.
请吧，我坚持
Please, l insist.
好吧
Okay.
(BOTH LAUGHING)
我想该结束了
Guess this is it.
是啊，不错的冒险呢
Yeah. Quite an adventure.
旅途已经结束了
End of the line.
是啊
Yes.
我猜在你在迷你苏达那儿 可不会有这些奇遇吧?
Guess things like this don't happen in Tiny-soda.
迷你苏达
Tiny-soda?
- 哦 等会儿 是明尼苏达  - 对
Wait, Minnesota. Yeah.
这个名字不错 事实上有趣极了
That's very good. That's very funny actually.
- 路易兹! 路易兹 你在这儿吗?  嘿 伙计
Luiz! Are you here, Luiz? Hey, buddy!
我带了几个朋友来见你
l got some friends l want you to meet.
(BARKING)
(SCREAMING)
Go!
内脚外脚，内脚外脚
BOTH: lnside, outside, inside, outside!
(WHIMPERING)
(LAUGHING)
抓到你们了... 不错
l got you's good.
什么?
What?
我本来能一口咬破你们的喉咙
l could've ripped your throats out, but l didn't.
但我没有
But l could've.
卢易斯！别吓坏我朋友了
Hey, Luiz! Stop scaring my friends.
嘿 拉斐 快过来!
Hey, Rafi, come here!
你到哪儿去了?
Where you've been?
你看起不错嘛
You look good.
等等 路易兹是一只斗牛犬?
Wait. Luiz is a bulldog?
你对狗有什么偏见吗?
You got something against dogs?
他们对着我口水乱飞时 就会有
l do when they're drooling on me.
人家生病了嘛…
lt's a medical condition.
不 老兄 我们真的需要你帮忙
No, hey, amigo, we really need you.
她好刻薄，老哥
She's mean, bro.
卢易斯拜托了，
Luiz, come on, please, please.
我们需要你帮忙
We need your help.
嗯
Hmm.
我想我知道怎么做了
l think l know what to do.
你确定这安全吗？
Are you sure this is safe?
当然，完全没危险
Sure. There's nothing to it.
如果有什么差错 就喊出来 一定要够大声
Now, if something goes wrong, scream really loud!
因为戴着这玩意 我听不太清
Because l can't hear too good with this thing on.
嘿 拉斐! 把开关按下去!
Hey, Rafi! Get the switch, please.
别担心 这机器是专业的
Don't worry. He's a professional.
(ROARING)
(BOTH GASPING)
(WHIMPERING)
尽量不要动
LUIZ: Now, try not to move!
这玩意在套头上 我也看不太清
l can't really see out of this thing, either!
(DISTORTED SCREAMING)
嘿 你们在哪儿?
Hey! Where did you go?
(GROANS) Eww!
真恶心
Gross.
但我自由了
But l'm free.
珠儿，我们自由了
Jewel! Jewel! We're free!
黏乎乎的 但自由了!
Slimy, but free.
可能还脏兮兮的 但是总算自由了
Contaminated probably, but free.
你相信吗 我们终于...
Can you believe it's finally...
(WHOOPING)
成功了
...over.
太棒了!
Yeah!
伙计们 快来 我们走吧!
Come on, guys, let's go!
我们还在这儿站着干吗? 今天可是狂欢节!
What are we standing around for? lt's Carnaval!
(ALL WHOOPING)
Oh, yeah!
Yep.
我知道你现在的感受
l know just how you feel.
看着他们在空中翱翔
Watching them up there
使你情不自禁想追上他们 把他们咬在嘴里
makes you want to chase them and grab them in your mouth
一口咬断他们的头
and bite their heads off, huh?
(LAUGHING)
我是在玩笑 兄弟
l'm just kidding, bro.
能追他们 我就满足了
Yeah, chasing them is plenty.
我要展翅飞翔 就像鸟儿一样
l'm flying, flying just like a bird!
珠儿 你就是一只鸟啊
Jewel, but you are a bird!
嘿 你要到哪儿去?
Hey! Where you going?
布鲁?
Blu?
布鲁 你怎么了?
Blu, what's wrong?
没什么 一切都很好
Nothing. Everything is perfect.
你去你的雨林
You'll be off to the rainforest,
我回到琳达的怀抱 就像之前我们计划的那样
l'll be back with Linda, just like we planned.
嘿 你们两个! 别废话了 起飞吧
Hey, birds! Stop yapping and start flapping!
我们走!
Let's go!
我想 也许 可能 我...
l guess, l thought, maybe...
怎么 你要来明尼苏达?
What? That you'd come to Minnesota?
那很好 我想我可以 为你做一条头巾
Great, l guess l'll knit you a scarf.
不 我不是这个意思
No, that's not what l meant.
听着 珠儿 我可不能一辈子这样
Look, Jewel, l can't spend my life
你飞到哪儿 我就走路跟到哪儿
walking around following you wherever you're going.
嘿 你不能飞 又不是我的错
Hey, it's not my fault you can't fly.
尴尬了
Awkward.
好了 好了
Okay, okay.
你们知道吗? 这样很好 坦诚相待
You know what? This is good. Just clear the air.
说出你们的心里话
Just be completely honest with each other.
说心里话是吧! 那好 我说心里话
You want honesty? Fine, l can be honest.
我不属于这儿
l don't belong here.
事实上 我一开始就没想来这儿
ln fact, l never wanted to come here in the first place.
而且... 而且
And... And...
你知道吗?
And you know what?
我讨厌桑巴舞!
l hate samba.
(GASPING)
(SOBBING)
嘿 这有点扯远了
Hey! That's a little too far.
叫那个讨厌的鸟收回这句话
Make the mean bird take it back.
不 我偏说
Yeah, l said it.
每首歌听起来都一样
Every song sounds exactly the same.
迪科嗒科呀呀呀…
Tico, taco, ya, ya, ya Tico, taco, ya, ya, ya
(GROANS)
我要回家了
l'm tico, taco out of here.
好啊! 再见了 宠物
Fine! See you around, pet!
不不不，别走了
No, wait, wait. Come back!
你们是一对! 他是罗密欧 你就是他的朱丽叶
You belong together! You are Juliet to his Romeo!
虽然 他们最后都死了
Sure, they both die in the end,
但你们知道我的意思!
but you get my point!
年轻人的恋爱 总是这么富有戏剧色彩
Young love. Always so melodramatic.
好了 小伙子们 跟着她去吧
All right, boys, go after her.
布鲁!回到这儿来 快回来!
Blu! Come back here. Come on!
我准备好去狂欢节了!
Yeah! l'm ready for Carnaval!
谁想吃着水果和我...
Who wants to ride in my
同行?
fruit.
他们不带上我就走了
You left without me.
我被落下了
That's messed up.
珠儿! 珠儿!
Jewels! Jewels!
等等!
Wait up!
(CRYING)
到哪儿去啊 美女?
Going somewhere, pretty bird?
哦  我正准备去把你的眼珠挖出来呢!
Yeah. l was just on my way to claw your eyes out!
珠儿!
Jewel!
冷静，冷静
Temper, temper.
现在跟我来 亲爱的
Now come along, my dear.
我们要去游行了
We're going to a parade.
人人都爱游行
Everybody loves a parade.
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
放开我!
Let go of me!
给我站住！
Hey! Get back here!
没人能欺负佩德罗的朋友 从来没有！
Ain't nobody messing with a friend of Pedro, l ain't having it!
开打！
lt's on!
你看见那家伙的利爪了吗?
Did you see the talons on that guy?
利爪?
Talons?
还是下次 再收拾他吧
Maybe it's on next time.
(SCREAMING)
拉斐 救命 救命!
Help! Help! Little help!
拉斐尔 别跟着我了
Rafael, quit following me.
你走错方向了
You're going in the wrong direction.
狂欢节不是在那边吗?
lsn't Carnaval that way?
我不去狂欢节
l'm not going to Carnaval.
我是要回家
No, l'm going home.
但是你不是很喜欢狂欢节吗?
But l thought you loved Carnaval.
是的 但是我更爱我的家人
l do. But l love my family much more.
这是我用这里作的选择
And that's a choice l made with this.
而不是这儿
Not with this.
- 布鲁! 布鲁!  - 布鲁!
NICO: Blu! PEDRO: Hey, Blu! Blu!
刚才我正飞着 突然看见那个带着
l was flying and then l saw this big cockatoo!
忍者利爪的凤头鹦鹉
With big ninja talons!
这只鹦鹉丑的很 从哪儿看都很丑
This cockatoo was ugly! Anyway, that's not the point.
然后珠儿遇到他了，就被他抓走了
And then Jewel was there, and he snatched Jewel up.
然后他就类似：
Like, he snatched her up. And then he was like,
“你要跟我走吗，小公主？”
"You're coming with me, you little princess."
然后珠儿就这样 啪! 啪!
And Jewel was like,
"我不是公主 放开我"
"l ain't your princess, leave me alone."
- 然后我就 "嘿!"  - 然后他就 "啥!"
And l was like, "What?" Then he was like, "What?"
够了！告诉我究竟怎么了！
Stop! Just tell me what happened.
他把珠儿抓了起来
He got Jewel, man!
他还要带珠儿去游行
And he's taking her to the parade.
这都是我的错
This is all my fault.
我们起飞！
Let's fly.
狂欢节 我们来了!
Carnaval, here we come!
嘿 臭狗 把我喷回来了
Hey, dog, l'm drowning back here!
这趟飞行你会湿透的!
You will get wet on this ride!
快啊 快啊 快啊
Come on, come on, come on.
这些家伙哪去了?
Where are these guys?
(LAUGHING) Whoa!
不错 很漂亮
Yes. Nice.
漂亮极了
Very nice.
马塞尔!
Marcel!
哦 天啊
Oh, boy.
还有鸡
We're a chicken!
(LAUGHING)
来吧 费尔南多 跳啊
Come on, Fernando! Dance!
(MIMICKING CHICKEN)
蠢货
ldiots.
借过!
Excuse me.
Coming through!
小心你的脚
Watch your feet.
哎呀 抱歉
Whoops! Sorry.
走吧 通过
Go ahead. Come in.
等一下 请停下来
Wait. Stop, please.
只限表演者入内
Performers only.
Huh?
(LAUGHING) Wow.
Cyanopsitta spixii.
(SQUAWKING)
图里奥?
Tulio?
琳达 我刚刚只是...
Linda. l was just...
我看起来很滑稽 是吗?
l look ridiculous, don't l?
(SAY YOU, SAY ME PLAYING)
# 说你 说我 #
Say you, say me
# 就像我们以前谈得那样 #
Say it for always
# 这是最好的方式 #
That's the way it should be
抱歉
Sorry.
哦!
Oh!
游行! 就要开始了
The parade. lt's about to start.
好
Okay.
一位女巫 进去吧
Go ahead.
听着 只要跟着我做
Okay, just follow my lead.
表现自然点
Act naturally.
(SQUAWKING)
Whoa!
你还好吗?
Are you okay?
走吧
Yeah. Come on.
布鲁？布鲁！
Blu? Blu!
Blu! Blu!
(SPEAKING PORTUGUESE)
等等 不 不 不
What? Wait, wait! No, no.
我在找一只蓝鸟 鸟
l am looking for a bluebird. Birdo?
什么鸟？快走快走
Birdo! Yes!
Okay.
等等 你在干什么? 图里奥!
Wait! What are you doing?
图里奥!
Tulio!
嘿! 让我出去!
Hey! Let me out!
(SQUAWKING)
(COUGHING)
图里奥!
Tulio!
(GASPING)
不太对劲 不太对劲 这是...
This is not good. This is not good. This is...
(SAMBA MUSIC PLAYING)
中大奖了
Cheese and sprinkles.
好吧 你现在可以放我下去了
Okay, you can bring me down now!
我想我们讲得很明白了
l think we're done here!
(PEOPLE BOOING)
我觉得他们喜欢看我舞动
l think they like my moves.
嘿 跳起来 我的孩子
Hey. Keep dancing, egg-boy.
一个在笼中 另一个马上也要来了
One down and one to go.
你永远找不到他
You'll never find him.
他已经走了
He's already gone.
我不需要去找他
l don't need to find him.
他会来找你的
He'll find you.
这才爽嘛!
This is the spit!
好啊，宝贝
Yeah, baby!
现在我可以继续疯狂了
Now, l could get my freak on!
拜托卢易斯
Luiz, please!
先救人 一会儿再狂欢
Rescue first. Freak later.
- 走吧  - 行人们 别挡我的道!
Come on! Out of my way, people!
好吧 朋友们
All right, guys!
我先走一步 看看珠儿在哪儿
l'll fly ahead and look for Jewel.
女士们 你们好啊
Hello, ladies.
大鼻子在那儿 等等我们!
Mr. Big-nose! Hold up!
(SPEAKING PORTUGUESE)
什么啊!
What?
琳达! 不好意思 不好意思
Linda? Excuse me. Excuse me.
琳达!
Linda!
(SPEAKING PORTUGUESE)
说英语!
ln English!
琳达 你要扭屁股
Linda! Linda!
You've got to shake your tushy!
不 我们明尼苏达州人可不扭屁股
No! We don't shake our tushies in Minnesota!
(GROANING)
(LUIZ BARKING)
激动的狗儿来了
Hot dog! Coming through!
布鲁!
Blu!
图里奥! 图里奥! 我看到布鲁了!
Tulio! Tulio! l saw Blu!
你说什么?
What?
撑住布鲁! 我这就来救你
Hold on, Blu! l'm coming for you!
(EXCLAIMING lN PORTUGUESE)
布鲁!
Blu!
琳达
Linda!
是琳达吗?
Linda?
等等
Wait!
(EXCLAIMING)
布鲁 我们找到她了
Blu, we found them!
她在一个奇怪的鸡形彩车上
She's on some weird chicken float!
快来!
Come on!
我们先去救珠儿吧
Let's go get Jewel.
等等 布鲁! 你去哪儿啊?
Wait, Blu! Where are you going?
(WHOOPS)
好吧
Okay.
(LAUGHS)
(EXCLAIMS)
(PEOPLE CHEERING)
(SPEAKING PORTUGUESE)
我看到小蓝了，他骑在一只斗牛犬上
l saw Blu! He's riding on a bulldog!
你说什么?
What?
(BARKING)
(PANTING)
他们在那儿 就是那辆彩车
There they are! That's the float!
那彩车本身就是个悲剧
That float is a crime in itself!
他在那儿!
There he is!
- 嘿 珠儿  - 布鲁?
Hey, Jewel. Blu!
- 我来救你了  - 不要
l'm gonna get you out of here. No.
不要 布鲁 你不能在这儿 你赶快走 奈杰要...
No, Blu, you can't be here. You have to go. Nigel...
你好啊 可爱的小鸟
Hello, pretty bird.
你能加入我们的小游戏 可真好
So kind of you to join our little soir
拜托，你觉得我会独自来吗？
Come on. You really think l came alone?
我有三只全里约最牛、最猛、最疯的…
l got three of the roughest, meanest
鸟儿作我的援军
craziest birds in all of Rio right behind me.
(PEDRO WHOOPING)
你知道是谁的，我们有救了！
You heard that, guys? We're saved!
That's right.
- 我觉得他是在说我们 - 哦
l think he means us.
Oh.
爱情 真是又强大又愚蠢的东西
Love. lt's such a powerful and stupid thing.
(LAUGHING)
哦 是的 好样的 奈杰
Yes. Well done, Nigel.
(HONKING)
(DANCERS EXCLAIMING)
不好意思 不好意思
Excuse me. Excuse me.
借过一下
Out of the way.
抱歉 等等 等一下!
Sorry. Wait! Wait!
我们成功了! 嘿 马塞尔
We actually made it! Hey, Marcel!
明年我们可以再玩一次吗? 求你了 求你了
Can we do this again next year? Please? Please?
好吗，后年也来？
Could l drive next year, too?
等等 回来!
Wait! Come back!
(PANTING)
上车!
Get in!
我不清楚我是怎么上来的
l don't know how l got up here,
但是我永远不会下去!
but l ain't never coming down!
(WHOOPING)
过来 小子
Come on, kid.
我来救你们出去
l'm gonna get you guys out of here.
- 你以为你在做什么?  - 没什么
What do you think you're doing?
Nothing.
你真不应该那么做 过来
You shouldn't have done that. Come on.
Ow!
别管他了！
Just forget him!
把鸟放好！
Get the birds!
他们要跑了
They're getting away.
那我们瞧瞧吧
We'll see about that.
小心！
Watch out!
我们成功了 伙计们!
We did it, boys.
对啊 我们是最棒的
Yes! We did it. We're the best!
那是一辆彩车吗?
ls that a float?
看上面的装饰
Wow! Look at the detail on that thing.
起飞啊 你个蠢货 起飞啊!
Pull up you, idiot!
Pull up!
(ALL SCREAMING)
布鲁!布鲁!
Blu! Blu!
哦 布鲁
Oh, Blu.
(SOBBING)
对不起 伊娃 我今天没法回家吃晚饭了
Sorry, Eva, l'm not gonna be home for dinner.
(GRUNTING)
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
我要像开易拉罐那样 把它打开
l'm gonna pop this cage open like a soda can.
瞧啊 打开了!
Now, that's popping!
快点 我们还要救其他人
Hurry. We got to help the others.
我是只漂亮鸟 我是只漂亮鸟
l'm a pretty bird, l'm a pretty bird.
谁是漂亮鸟，我是漂亮鸟
Who's a pretty bird?l'm a pretty bird.
漂亮鸟 我是只漂亮鸟
Pretty bird, l'm a pretty bird.
快跑!
Come on!
我出来了!
l'm out!
(BEEPING)
阳光！
The light!
飞，飞，飞
Go! Go! Go!
自由！
Freedom!
Geronimo!
（印地安人民族英雄）
(ALL CHEERING)
来吧 快点 我们要逃出去!
Come on! Come on! We need to get out!
等等 等一下!
Wait, wait, wait!
没事的 嘿 没事的
lt's okay. Hey, it's okay.
我们会一起想出办法的
We'll figure this out together. Right?
(SCREAMING)
放开他!
Let him go!
Ow!
珠儿!
Jewel!
我的翅膀
My wing.
哦 小可怜
Oh, pity.
现在我们有两只残废的不能飞的鸟
Now we have two useless, flightless birds.
(NIGEL LAUGHING)
Huh?
不给力啊，老兄，不给力
Not cool, man. Not cool!
(NIGEL SCREAMING)
Uh-oh.
(SCREAMING)
我们要坠机了!
We're going down!
来吧 剪刀 石头 布
Okay, okay.
Rock, paper, scissors...
降落伞!
Chute!
再见了 饭桶们!
Hasta la vista, losers!
嘿！ 等等我们!
Hey! Wait for us!
加农炮!
Cannonball!
布鲁!
Blu!
不要!
No!
(JEWEL SCREAMING)
(SCREAMING)
布鲁 你疯了! 你在干什么?
Blu, you're crazy! What are you doing?
我不能让你这样离开我
l'm not gonna let you go!
我们是拴在一起的两只鸟 忘了吗?
We're chained-to-each-other birds, remember?
(HEART BEATING)
哇
Wow.
布鲁 你在飞!
Blu! You're flying!
是啊! 哦 噢！
Yeah! Woo-hoo!
我在飞 我真的在飞!
l'm flying! l'm really flying.
你是对的 我不是只鸵鸟! 我不是鸵鸟!
You're right, l'm not an ostrich. l'm not an ostrich!
(WHOOPING)
What? (EXCLAIMING)
爸 快看!
Dad! Look!
蠢货!
ldiots.
(BIRDS SQUAWKING)
琳达!
Linda!
布鲁?
Blu?
是布鲁! 看 图里奥 是布鲁!
lt's Blu! Look, Tulio, it's Blu!
他在飞
And he's flying.
我的布鲁在飞
My Blu is flying!
He's flying.
(GASPING)
(SQUAWKS)
来 让我瞧瞧
Here, let me see.
别担心
Don't worry.
我会照顾你的
l'll take care of you.
(BOTH lMITATING EXPLOSION)
这才是我勇敢的孩子
That's my big, brave boy.
# 所有鸟类 披着羽毛 #（请继续观赏）
All the birds of a feather
# 各有所需 取其所好 #
Do what we love most of all
# 星月之下 拨弄吉他 #
Moon and the stars Strumming guitars
# 狂欢节庆 华丽壮大 #
That's why we love Carnaval
# 热爱我们的丛林生活 #
Loving our life in the jungle
# 一切都那么狂热自由 #
Everything's wild and free
# 从不孤独 这是我们的家乡 #
Never alone 'Cause this is our home
# 仿佛有人 挥动法杖 #
Magic can happen for real
# 就在里约 #
ln Rio
# 实现梦想 #
All by itself
By itself
# 你能看到 它的美妙 #
You can't see it coming
# 别的地方 无法找到 #
You can't find it anywhere else
# 我是桑巴歌神
l'm the capoeira king-a
歌圣 歌王 歌圣
King-a, king-a, king-a
歌王 #
King-a!
# 我受欢迎 因为我有性感翅膀 #
Birds like me 'cause l'm a hot wing-a
# 如天使一样 #
Pedro, hot-a-wing-a
# 这里的人都爱桑巴 #
Here everybody loves samba
# 我爱桑巴 #
l like the samba
# 你要用心去感受它 #
Rhythm you feel in your heart
# 我是桑巴舞王 #
l'm the samba master
# 美人真情 围绕左右 人生至此 夫复何求 #
Beauty and love What more could you want?
# 实现梦想 #
Fantasy can be for real
# 就在里约 #
ln Rio
# 用心倾听 #
Here's something else
Something else
# 你能感受 它的美妙 #
You just feel it happening
# 别的地方 无法找到 #
You won't find it anywhere else
我爱你 里约!
l love you, Rio!
(GROANS)
(EXCLAIMS)
(LAUGHING)
(GASPS)
(TELLING THE WORLD PLAYING)
# 每一片真心 我都会献出 #
Every part in my heart l'm giving out
# 每一支歌谣 我都会吟唱 #
Every song on my lips l'm singing out
# 每一丝畏惧 我都会放下 #
Any fear in my soul l'm letting go
# 每个人来问 我都会回答 #
And anyone who asks l'll let them know
# 我的唯一 我的爱 我会大声地说是她 #
She's the one, she's the one l say it loud
# 我的唯一 我的爱 我会自豪地说是她 #
She's the one, she's the one l say it proud
# 敲响钟声 敲响铃 我向世界呐喊 #
Ring a bell, ring a bell For the whole crowd
# 敲响钟声 敲响铃 #
Ring a bell, ring a bell
# 我向世界呐喊 #
l'm telling the world
# 我找到了我的她 #
That l've found a girl
# 可与我白头偕老的她 #
The one l can live for
# 可令我一生厮守的她 #
The one who deserves
# 每一片真心 我都会献出 #
Every part in my heart l'm giving out
# 每一支歌谣 我都会吟唱 #
Every song on my lips l'm singing out
# 每一丝畏惧 我都会放下 #
Any fear in my soul l'm letting go
# 每个人来问 我都会回答 #
And anyone who asks l'll let them know
# 我的唯一 我的爱 我会大声地说是她 #
She's the one, she's the one l say it loud
# 我的唯一 我的爱 我会自豪地说是她 #
She's the one, she's the one l say it proud
# 敲响钟声 敲响铃 我向世界呐喊 #
Ring a bell, ring a bell For the whole crowd
# 敲响钟声 敲响铃 #
Ring a bell, ring a bell
# 我向世界呐喊 #
l'm telling the world
# 我找到了我的她 #
That l've found a girl
# 可与我白头偕老的她 #
The one l can live for
# 可令我一生厮守的她 #
The one who deserves
# 给了我的光 #
To give all the light
# 一个飞翔的理由 #
A reason to fly
# 可与我白头偕老的她 #
The one l can live for
# 一个飞翔的理由 #
A reason for life
# 我向世界呐喊 #
l'm telling the world
# 我找到了我的她 #
That l've found a girl
# 可与我白头偕老的她 #
The one l can live for
# 可令我一生厮守的她 #
The one who deserves
# 给了我的光 #
To give all the light
# 一个飞翔的理由 #
A reason to fly
# 可与我白头偕老的她 #
The one l can live for
# 一个飞翔的理由 #
A reason for life
(LET ME TAKE YOU
TO RIO PLAYING)
Rio, Rio, Rio,
Get 'em one more time
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
Fly over the ocean
like an eagle, eagle
Then we can chill
in my gazebo, gazebo
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
Fly over the ocean
like an eagle, eagle
Then we can chill
in my gazebo, gazebo
All in together now
How you like the weather now?
Rio, Rio, oh
Right here show me now
You know how to put it down
Rio, Rio, oh
You got a light, girl,
turn it on
Here's mine, turn me on
Rio, Rio, oh
You got a wild side
Let it out
l'm gonna make
you bring it out
Rio, Rio, oh
Shake it up fast
Wind it up slow now
Just move your body, girl
Work it to the floor,
Let your body go now
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
Fly over the ocean
like an eagle, eagle
Then we can chill
in my gazebo, gazebo
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
Fly over the ocean
like an eagle, eagle
Then we can chill
in my gazebo, gazebo
Let me take you to Rio
Show you all around
de Janeiro
Keep your back down,
Be like a drummer
Don't act shy,
Girl, you know you wanna
Dance, dance, dance,
Dance, dance, dance
Girl, you know you wanna
Dance, dance, dance,
Dance, dance, dance
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
Fly over the ocean
like an eagle, eagle
Then we can chill
in my gazebo, gazebo
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
Fly over the ocean
like an eagle, eagle
Then we can chill
in my gazebo, gazebo
Let me take you to Rio, Rio
Fly over the ocean
like an eagle, eagle
Then we can chill
in my gazebo, gazebo
(FUNKY MONKEY PLAYING)
Everybody,
Gather round
Brand new dance
Going down
Funky, funky monkey
CHORUS: What you doing?
lt don't matter
who you know
You can do it
Gather round
Move your body to the beat
And let your monkey body
move your funky feet
And you like it
'cause it feels
so good to do
Funky, funky monkey
(MAN RAPPING lN PORTUGUESE)
lt don't matter
Who you know
You can do it
Gather round
Move your body
All around
Act like you just saw
something sticky on the ground
But you like it 'cause
it smells so good to you
Funky, funky monkey
English - US - PSDH